# **Monisha Gopalan**

**Address** Via Giambellino 22, 35129, Padova, Italy.

E-mail moni2996@gmail.com Mobile +39 3491897796

Date of Birth 29 December 1996 **Nationality** Indian LinkedIn

https://www.linkedin.com/in/monisha-gopalan/



### **SUMMARY**

As an enthusiastic AI Scientist Intern at a startup focusing on AI for finance, I bring a strong academic background with double masters in STEM, majoring in physics, and diverse interdisciplinary research experience. I specialize in Portfolio Optimization and have a solid grasp of fundamental finance principles and statistics. My skill set includes advanced programming in Deep Learning Techniques, Monte Carlo Simulations, and Numerical Methods.

### **SKILLS**

Programming	<ul> <li>Python (advanced) – NumPy, Pandas, PyTorch, SciPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-learn</li> <li>R – Quantmod, jrvFinance, fOptions, PortfolioAnalytics, PerformanceAnalytics</li> </ul>			
	- SQL	- MATLAB (ba	ısic)	- C (basic)
Certifications	<ol> <li>Quantitative Finance with R – Udemy – July 2023.</li> <li>Introduction to Portfolio Construction and Analysis with Python – Coursera – April 2023.</li> <li>Data Analysis with Python – freeCodeCamp - March 2023.</li> </ol>			
IT Skills	- AWS Sagemaker	- Git	-PyCharm	
	- Linux Terminal	- LaTeX	-Microsoft Office – Word, Excel, PowerPoint	
Soft skills	- Problem solving	- Thinking Differently		- Analysis
	- Communication skills	- Planning		- Teamwork
Languages	<ul> <li>English (C2) – Fluent spoken and written. TOEFL iBT: 106/120</li> <li>Italian – Basic spoken and written.</li> <li>German – Basic</li> </ul>			

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

03.2023 - 01.2024

Al Scientist - Intern | Ipazia, Milan, Italy.

#### **Deep Learning of Portfolio Optimization**

- analysed large-scale time-series datasets on AWS and developed a deep learning model with LSTM using PyTorch Lightning to directly optimise portfolio Sharpe ratio.
- currently engaged in pioneering research to develop a novel architecture, incorporating Hopfield layers and Transformers by positional encoding time-series data, while contributing to a scikit library.
- visualised portfolio results by comparing weight allocations with benchmark portfolios, in addition to equity curve analysis and portfolio metrics.

11.2022 - 03.2023

Master's Thesis Student | University of Padova, Italy.

Real Space Renormalization Group Techniques for lattice systems.

• conducted extensive study of 4 real-space renormalization group methods applied to Ising and Potts models on lattices.

• implemented Monte Carlo method for renormalization group using the efficient Wulff cluster sampling algorithm.

11.2018 - 07.2019

**Master's Thesis Student** | *Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru.* 

Phase-Field Modelling of Eutectoid Transformation in Ternary systems.

- developed a C program that utilizes numerical methods to solve a one-dimensional sharp interface model with a Stefan boundary condition.
- analysed the variation of the growth constant by solving the model for 10 different supersaturation values.

11.2017 - 05.2018

**Bachelor's Thesis Student** | *Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru.* 

Triple point fermions in Full-Heusler compounds using first principle calculations.

- enhanced proficiency in Linux operating systems and command-line interfaces.
- utilized Cray supercomputer clusters and software packages: VASP, WannierTools, Phonopy to compute energy band diagrams and check stability of compounds.
- identified 7 new compounds with triple point fermions.
- presented progress updates every week in the lab group meetings.

## **EDUCATION**

10.2019 - 07.2023

Master's degree in Physics | University of Padova, Italy.

**Grade: 87%** 

- Models of Theoretical Physics, Statistical mechanics, Stochastic Calculus, Bayesian Inference, Markov chain Monte Carlo simulation methods.
- Neural networks, Deep learning Supervised Learning, Unsupervised Learning, Deep Reinforcement Learning.

08.2018 - 07.2019

**Master of Science in Materials Science** | *Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru.* 

**Grade: 71%** 

• Modelling and simulation using Python – Numerical Methods, Molecular and Monte Carlo Methods.

08.2014 - 05.2018

**Bachelor of Science (Research) in Materials Science** | Indian Institute of Science

**Grade: 70%** 

- (Minor: Mathematics) Real Analysis, Linear Algebra, Multivariable Calculus, Probability and Statistics, Group theory, Topology.
- Algorithms, Data structures and Programming using C; Scientific Computing and Numerical methods using MATLAB.